hello and welcome it's January 24th 2023
we're in active bookstream number
001.07 on governing continuous
transformation off to you blue
so we are the active inference Institute
a participatory online Institute that is
communicating learning and practicing
applied active inference you can reach
us at all of these social media links
this is a recorded and archived live
stream so please provide us with
feedback so that we can improve upon our
work all backgrounds and perspectives
are welcome here and we will be
following good video etiquette for live
streams again if you'd like to
participate act inference
activeinference.org is our main website
and there's a link to get involved and
join many of the ongoing collaborative
projects or live streams or both
uh this is as Daniel said bookstream
1.07 so it's our seventh
contextualization video
um on this book governing continuous
transformation by Bijan kesri so we will
just jump right into it
um I'm blue I'm an independent
researcher in New Mexico and I will pass
it off to Daniel
all right I'm Daniel I'm a researcher in
California and just happy to see this
series continue
tell
and um to Tyler I'm a profile designer
and our researcher in California
great
um so we are in part two free energy
governance of this textbook
um and the name of this chapter is
cognition from superposition to reality
um and so I think that that kind of
hints to some Quantum stuff that might
be elaborated more towards the end of
this chapter and in the next chapter
um and just a few keywords for this
um chapter
but still quite a bit of content here so
Tyler do you want to read the start of
the abstract do you mind
sounds good can you guys hear me okay
great
um all right attention base for you and
inactivist approach address feg's
cognition Dimension to this day strategy
management research is not entirely each
chain from its very path dependency of
putting perception ahead of action I.E
putting environment ahead of strategy
while abv's structure cognition Nexus is
fpg's critical building block ABV Iran
erroneously trades action as a
consequence of perception once we
Embrace attention as action generated we
start understanding that clever analysis
and form of belief updating follows
action generated stimuli not the other
way around ABV is trapped in the old
school limitations opposed by bounded
rationality in the discontinuous and
distributed Quantum World agents
boundary rationality is meaningless as
enacted in for instance Powers the world
to deliver supervisory signal
effectively agents offload the burden of
cognition to the environment boundary
rationality is replaced by extended
cognition the betterness of human
cognition is effectively neutralized
blue intake next one
there are at least as many reality model
models as there are economic actors
every organization chooses akin to
holding acting upon a light torch in the
Darkness
which environmental significance to
attend to whatever the torch highlights
is equivalent to breaking a Quantum wave
of probabilities moving from
superposition to Reality intermediated
by the Markov blanket
environmental enactment is essentially a
purpose-directed interactive inferential
and social learning sense making process
all right so there are two sections to
this chapter the first is
attention-based View and the second is
an activist approach
um so Tyler do you want to take this
slide
sure all right so attention-based view
so we actually touched on this a couple
streams ago in the context of when we
introduced this was that abhijan was
going through different models of
thinking about firm good cognition and
they're all Limited in their own sense
including attention-based medium we'll
go deeper into why attention-based view
is limited but also has important ways
of thinking about how pharmacognition
works and so the general idea of it is
that attention is a limited resource and
that permeates through all levels of the
hierarchy of an organization so on the
individual level you have limited
attention that bows the the level the
the balance or condition of what you're
able to understand and perceive and
decisions you're able to make and the
boundedness of your individual cognition
uh bubbles up into a social context
which bubbles the kind of decisions a
group of people can make and then that
finally bubbles up into your
organizational cognition which manifests
through different rules positions
players and resources
um so this is just to say like hey we
only have so many things that we can
spend our time and energy on and that
manifests at larger levels
um in the kinds of rules that we make
within an organization
um blue Dano anything you would add here
yeah so I can read this claim well
attention-based views structure
cognition Nexus is a critical building
block of free energy governance
fundamentally attention-based view
suffers from severe shortcomings that
weaken its relevance to practice by
highlighting some of attention-based
views most fundamental weaknesses we
should further cement the case for free
energy governance as a meta Theory
connecting in circular causality
structure cognition and capabilities
once we understand how the Bayesian
brain is building a model of its world
we start seeing how anachronistic and
full of friction are deep-rooted
conceptions of organizational attention
are
um do you guys have anything to add here
okay cool all right so uh bounded
rationality so this was
um a concept that Bijan brought up here
in this chapter and it was introduced um
by Herbert Simon the term in like 1957
and I pulled this from the Stanford
um Encyclopedia of philosophy so his
um introduction of this term was a
shorthand for his position against
neoclassical economics and his call to
replace the perfect rationality
assumptions of homo economicus with the
conception of rationality tailored to
cognitively limited agents
um and so like this little figure
um
here shows like the cognitive
limitations and in in imperfect
information and time constraints that
we're faced with when we have to make a
decision so we don't we always like are
limited by what we can hold in our brain
and like the view of the information
that we have and like we were talking
about like complexity
um like Computing Pi like we could get a
more accurate you know uh numerical
digit of of Pi but but we're limited
like by time like if we go on and on and
on we could get more and more accurate
but like why like is 3.14 good enough
because I can pull it up in like a split
second from my from memory
um and so all of this like configures
our bounded rationality and um we use a
process that Herbert Simon introduced as
satisficing to make a sub-optimal
decision or like our best possible
decision with the bounded rationality
that we're faced with
um and uh a quote from the um Herbert
Simon Says broadly stated the task is to
replace the global rationality of
economic man with the kind of rational
behavior that is compatible with the
access to information and the
computational capacities that are
actually possessed by organisms
including men in the kind of
environments in which such organisms
exist
um Tyler do you want to read uh where
this founded rationality concept is
introduced in the chapter
sure yeah so so I think that the context
here is that he's trying to connect ABV
to biographicality by saying all right
well you have limited attention how does
a firm decide where his attention is
spent right like how do you make that
decision collectively so he says in ABV
top leadership's attention to the right
issues and solutions consider the source
the firm's competitive Advantage
essentially is content rather than
process center it confirms performance
bottleneck remains upper at your mom's
attention right on aggressionality the
critical question then is how in the
first place context is selected to
determine the tension or have all them
up Market signals connected with top
down upper extra long expectations and
predictions to determine attention and
so what it stands like ABV doesn't
really explain how that attention gets
directed in the first place uh ABV is
trapped in the old school limitations
opposed about rationality and
discontinuous and distributed Quantum
World agents bounded rationalities
meaningless as perceptual content it's
given in inner predictions and this is
precisely what allows the world to over
the supervisory signal effectively the
firm is offloading the burden of
condition to its environment so bound
rationality is extended is replaced by
extended cognition the Badness of human
cognition is effectively neutralized
blue Daniel I think to add there
yeah we'll go to the next slide where uh
we'll display more about extended
cognition
so um Extended cognition I took this
from this article by Mark spreeback uh
extended cognition takes the idea that
your mind is on your smartphone
literally so it says that human
cognitive States and processes sometimes
spill outside of our heads into objects
in our environment and this is something
that we've looked at and talked about
before in many ways like even with evil
I'm not sure if you guys talked about it
yesterday on the stream but in the
thinking like a state live stream that
we did we talked quite a bit about
extended cognition and cumulative
cultural Evolution and how like the the
a lot of our cognition is like out there
embedded in our environment so that we
don't have to think about it
um like when I grew up there was no
internet so we would have to like you
know I mean Colton like my son in the
car the other day asked me some question
and I was like you're gonna have to ask
Alexa or Google and and he was like will
you ask your phone for me and um it was
like some fact question like how many
bones are the body or something that I
couldn't remember on top of my head and
I said well wait till we get to school
and then I'll ask my phone because my
phone was like whatever playing music or
doing and I'm driving right
um and he was like that is so long like
like you can't wait 15 minutes to get to
school to like answer the question I was
like man when I was a kid if I wanted to
know the answer to this question like I
would have to go to the library look in
the card catalog find a book like or
encyclopedia or something oh it's a
goodness book of world record that's
what it was it was like the world's
smallest pancake or something like that
um and so like we would have to find the
book and then look it up in the book and
it would take days like if we could even
remember the question for that long and
he was like oh my God where would you
live
so like this kind of extended cognition
like we could just know everything with
a click of a few buttons is amazing
um do you guys have anything to add here
at extended cognition sorry I ramble
all right
um then maybe Tyler wants to talk about
channeling attention
cool so yeah I mean your extended
cognition is not just uh you as this
single known organization and it
actually encompasses
both your environment the The Firm
around it and also maybe the environment
around the firm like how's the attention
of that cognition get channeled like how
do you decide what matters what does it
matter
and so what John says is while ABV views
organizations as systems of structurally
distribute attention where stress for
channel detention ABV trees the process
of channeling as a black box so it's
like a framework for thinking about how
cognition is limited in organizational
context but it doesn't really tell you
like what's going on for that reason it
doesn't end up being super practical at
least in the John's telephone so he goes
on to say neither you EV nor you ABV
both fundamentally top-down oriented
Frameworks have given due consideration
to the dynamic interplay between top
management team TMT and the board of
directors more specifically there's no
transparent structural link between the
upper echelon level and field
intelligence for example the very
process that governs the two layers
interaction determining a firm's
attention and actions remains opaque and
so I think broadly what Beyond saying is
that especially like the inactivist
approach of thinking that how your
actions and the environment determine
your perception that's missing in ABV
and that's a critical aspect of
understanding how cognition happens in
an organization but specifically the
airplane between the board and the the
management team I wish you previous
streams he spent a lot of time
describing why that's a really critical
and important relationship uh for firm
cognition
um blue Dale anything you you got on
here
so I would just add that like um or
maybe emphasize the point that we talk
about a lot about top management here
and the board and that interaction and
then like the interactions between
different levels of the hierarchy like
from the top all the way to the bottom
and I think that that we emphasize the
importance of like the the feeding
forward and feeding back and like the
interaction between the layers and how
information is transmitted between them
but there's no um real concrete
um examples of how to to best do that
um and I think that this is like like
for me like not just in a firm but also
like in the body like how is that
information like transmitted like how
does like my big toe prioritize like
what goes to my brain like obviously if
I kick something really hard and hurt my
toe or like if I get like a hangnail or
like a like ingrown toenail or something
it really hurts but like otherwise my
toe like I don't even know it's ever
talking to my brain so it has to to like
provide salience somehow
um and how this is done and um I don't
know that's so critical for me I think
that that's like really at the heart of
all of um the active and Friends
hierarchical structuring stuff
all right
attentional coherence so
um here bishan quotes
um Ocasio and this is like a 2011
um
paper I guess or maybe book but he puts
a lot of emphasis on Ocasio as like one
of um like the people that like his work
really rests strongly upon so I
encourage you to read the chapter if you
want to learn more or go straight to
Ocasio itself so he says the interaction
of top down and bottom-up attentional
processes is also implicit in the wick
and Sutcliffe concept of the quality of
organizational attention and in the
re-rope analysis of attentional
triangulation combining attentional
stability top down attentional vividness
bottom up and attentional coherence
combining both
um and and he goes on to say that um
attention-based you cannot explain
attentional coherence and so getting at
what I just was saying about like the
interaction between the top down and
bottom up and like how that works um can
be explained in a tension-based view
maybe it can be explained in free energy
governance or we can maybe get some
guidance on how to best do that
hopefully in the coming chapters we'll
learn more do you guys have any comments
here
hey
I'm trying to read these claims for me
Tyler
sure so ABV Iran honestly treats action
as a consequence of attention and
perception according to ppf addiction
prediction processing framework actions
determine in circular causality to
stimulate that if your attention and
sense making while ABV is limiting a
critical foundation and looking
cognition structure the question arises
whether abv's attention will need to be
redefined as something more granular and
practical so tension not only is too
diffuse it's a cognitive concept that
also is hard to it's hard to meaning
meaningfully operationalize in the
context of continuous strategic renewals
so exactly what blue was saying on the
previous slide it doesn't ABV explains
like okay I understand why it's pension
being limited uh shapes affirms
cognition but like what do I even do
with that information like how is that
going to be impactful how can I model
that
um and the genre spending like well it's
not that useful right now but he's
teasing that maybe it could be with
active inference or free energy
governance
thank you
yeah like what is that something more
granular and practical like how do we
focus attention like how do we like
break attention up into like sub
components that are are more granular
and practical like
um yeah like what is in our our field of
view or what should be in our field of
view like um what we're looking at what
we're prioritizing and do those things
line up I don't know
um I could speculate all day but it's
hard to to know really what that more
granular and practical thing might be
what one other quick note on that is
there's the question of coherence and
adaptivity for example that student
answering their cell phone in the
classroom on the previous cartoon that
may have certain dimensions of
adaptivity or fulfill certain
preferences of One agent but not another
and then there's this question of action
orientation and so if we're always in
the business of asking about the
environment doing the market research
not thinking about the strategy taking
this sort of perception first mindset
there still is the question of
attentional coherence are we paying
attention and sense making putting all
the pieces together from what we're
perceiving
and also there is this inactive shift
which is incomplete but it's part of the
puzzle which is we want to be having
attention regimes of attention on our
action
and that brings together the embodiments
and the an active view with the
attentional view which as brought up
doesn't really describe what attention
is and still can be mobilized in a
passive setting but together we have
this active attention and that
flowers in active inference where
attention is internal action
so isn't it like pay attention to what
you're paying attention to is that like
a nested little little hint there
well in live stream 28 we saw a three
layer model of attention
and there is no single one way to model
any cognitive phenomena it's going to be
up to people in different settings to
understand
what treatments of attention are
insightful or useful or applicable
I don't know I think that that like
paying attention to what you're paying
attention to
um kind of gets
like a lot of attention in like the
business context or like even in like
um prioritizing like your to-do lists
right like are you just like fighting
fires all the time or are you like
making progress to do like things going
forward making progress on your own
goals so I think like I don't know that
might be might be a critical
um like governing variable right that um
so let me read this claim
in that regard predictive processing
framework in in the form of inactive
inference is potentially a critical
complement to and possibly substitute
for the attention-based view predictive
processing framework provides the
concepts and Logics that give new
meaning to the linkage of structure and
cognition according to predictive
processing framework prediction models
and predictions self-optimize as a
matter of pursuing Surprise minimization
by way of free energy minimization
it is strictly a priori not an attention
challenge but a purpose-directed
prediction challenge the evolution of
self-driving Vehicles provides an
exemplary illustration of this point
once the challenge was conceived as a
prediction rather than attention
challenge the road to Perfection is
simply a matter of continuous and
purpose-directed prediction error
minimization
and I don't know like what is really
meant by this like like the challenge of
self-driving was conceived as a
prediction like once people predicted
that it would happen
um I I'm not really sure like what
Bhajan means here
I could maybe take a stab at that one
um because I think what he's saying is
that like for a self-driving car that's
kind of thing that if you were being
using purely linear thinking only using
the things you know already about the
world like you would never a
self-driving car wouldn't be like an
obvious Next Step but you have to take
this leap of faith in action-oriented
week of faith into saying no we're going
to build a self-driving car and then
once you've decided that that's your
your path you're gonna go down now it's
just like optimization on that path
and so I think this he was after like
illustrating the inactivist approach of
like hey a self-driving vehicle is
nothing like obvious or self-evident
about that needing to happen but once
you decide it's going to happen then
it's a prediction problem
agree there's different
readings one way also not knowing the
self-driving car game
if we were in this passive
perception first world then there would
be uh the main issue to resolve would be
understand from noisy sensor readings
where is the location of a person and
producer uncertainty about where the
person is or what that object is
however once we see it in terms of this
continuous purpose-directed prediction
error minimization we're going to Center
the role of action gas break and turning
and a few other affordances that cars
have so instead of going for all the
decimal points on whether that's a
person or a mailbox or a cone
what does it look like to take this
unfolding action-oriented view where
you're aligning with your preferences
for example Not to cause harm to people
and then lesser priority Not to cause
harm to objects maybe steering away from
that object you can have a good policy
posterior on it's a good and likely
action without having all the decimals
of precision about the environments
so once we understand how essential
action is to the self-driving car it
reframes what we have to do with the
sensor data and it centralizes the
relevance of the strategy
yeah I do remember something about like
um some change in self-driving like in
the sensor system so maybe that like
references the um
like attention versus prediction problem
or maybe that's like being referred to
internally in there I'm not sure
okay so that sums up the attention based
view section and we're moving in now to
um the inactivist approach
um so this is like at the start of the
chapter
um quotes Thompson 2007 and says the
organism's environment is the sense it
makes of the world the environment is a
place of significance and Valence as a
result of the global action of the
organism
I'm so again taking this like
action-centric perspective
um and he quotes ramstead of Dallas 2020
by saying active inference is an active
inference and he says indeed the
essential question is how the firm
brings forth significance and Valence
that does not pre-exist but is the
result of action-centric and socially
constructed engagement with the outer
World equivalent to internally assigning
probabilities to the external hidden
unknown states in the form of a Marco
blanket this revealing of significance
and Valence then lays the foundation for
generating shared meaning and shared
expectations in the form of unique
interpretation models belief systems
underlying firm performance and survival
oh yeah so
we can go on to see what else he says so
he makes the claim
dafton week 1984 differentiate between
environment driven and
interpretation-driven approaches to
strategy making
um and in this big quote they say in
environment driven frames top managers
experience environments as Concrete Hard
measurable and determinant on the other
hand top managers of firms confronting
more unstable or unanalyzable
environments are thought to construct
course or enact a reasonable
interpretation that makes previous
action sensible
um thus they attempt to construct their
environments through their strategies
rather than developing strategies in
response to environments resulting in
strategy environment beliefs or
proactive Logics and he also says
despite wic's strong influence on
Strategic Management research to this
day the environment-driven approach
remains dominant
um so I think that this is like one of
the central themes that's emerging in
the book is um that that like the
environment is somewhere out there it's
some very real thing uh it's taken to be
like it's it is this way it's always
going to be this way
um and it's like
um and kind of something that Daniel and
I have talked about at length like
the niche as responding to the organism
the niche response to the organism just
as much as the organism responds to the
niche and whether or not the niche
includes other organisms in the
environment or not is kind of irrelevant
when we have things like books and
smartphones uh so this environment is is
changing
um and it's changing maybe so fast and
so much that this environment driven
framework is perhaps not effective so um
unstable or unanalyzable environments is
maybe like this discon discontinuous
environment that Bichon speaks of
um because the the environment's
changing fast like maybe faster than
it's ever changed before because of like
our Global connectivity and many other
reasons so so now maybe all environments
are unstable or unanalyzable or or more
unpredictable than they've been before
so that this um
constant update like or attempt to
attempting to construct the niche rather
than
um
viewing it as something stable is maybe
more important for firm persistence
glad you guys have any comments here
yeah I mean I just think on the the
second half of that of like very
unstable and unanalyzable environments
that really resonates in the start of
that context where uh a lot of times our
families will have no pretense of
knowing anything that's going on in the
environment like they're very uh
they're very clear about their ignorance
of the world instead they run small
experiments to kind of gauge what's
going on in the the external world and
then kind of construct the world view
from there rather than saying hey we
have this great business idea let's
scale this thing it's more like hey
let's discover who our users are um
which I think really uh
corresponds well with that second half
that were
also with our classical temperature
example
let's just say that we were in a house
and there was a heating element if we
think that over the time scale of days
things aren't going to change that much
we might look towards a strategy of
turning on and off the heater so dealing
with the environmental variability in
the niche we're in whereas if we're in
an open space so there's no point in
having any strategy of trying to heat
the local Air because it's just going to
get blown away in the next second then
you might Center decision making around
like finding a warmer location
and so when there's a more stable
environment then it puts us into a mode
of like understanding the variability
patterns the Circadian patterns and
temperature and responding with what we
have or maybe inventing something new to
respond to those regularities but when
there's the discontinuous and complex
environmental settings that this work is
focused on
It Centers this kind of creating one's
own Niche through action not just
modifying it more locally to do the best
one can
oh
um Tyler do you want to read this claim
do you mind
sure so every organization chooses can
holding a white porch in the darkness
which environmental significance to act
upon and tend to whatever the torch
highlights is equivalent to breaking a
Quantum wave of probabilities moving
from superposition to Reality
intermediated by the Markov blanket in
this regard strategy research is
challenged to be less mechanical
mechanical
mechanistically determined environmental
strategy but more Quantum strategy to
environment the quantum world is more
tenuous than the one I imagine and this
is actually quote from rebelli and this
is not Sean uh the quantum world is more
tenuous than the one imagined by old
physics it is made up of happenings get
discontinuous events without permanence
is a world of fine texture intricate and
fragile Venetian lace every interaction
is an event and it is these light and
ephemeral bends that weave reality not
the heavy objects charged with absolute
properties that are philosophy positive
and support of these events
oh thanks
um so
uh bishan goes on to say and I think
we'll we'll come back to this
um Quantum because I have some questions
here so we'll come back to this at the
closer to the end of this section
um but right now let's read this claim
um Bijan says the critical consideration
is how an organism or organism sorry too
much biology how an organization
transmorphs the sensing and sense making
activity at the individual level into a
firm's institutionalized environmental
enactment as a basis for continuous
strategic renewal
X-Men is essentially an interactive and
generative social learning sense making
process hence inactive inference dong at
Al elegantly addressed this micro
macrodichotomy they say while hypothesis
setting is an individual activity
hypothesis testing is an organizational
activity
according to smurchic and stubber
organization members actively form enact
their environments through social
interaction a pattern of enactment
establishes the foundation of
organizational reality and in turn has
effects in shaping future enactments the
task of strategic management in this
view is organization making to create
and maintain systems of shared meaning
that facilitate organized organized
action
um do you guys have any comments here
one thought I'm imagining uh a fleet of
boats the upper echelon View and the
board of directors specifically they may
not need to be concerned with the
minutia of move the wheel left move the
wheel right on this boat at that time
but they are as it says here the task of
strategic management in this view is
organization making
so that
justifies some of this upper echelon
Focus it's not coming I don't think from
a place of elitism or chauvinism about
those upper management groups but it's
especially targeting
to those who are in a position to be
involved in organization making which
isn't steering the boat
but allowing the agency and enactment to
happen in the front line requires
those not in the front line to take
The View that is being promoted here
rather than just imagine if we had
enough sensors on enough boats we could
have all of them viewed up in front of
us and then we could call out who should
turn left and who should turn right
with the three to eight board meetings
per year it's not going to happen so
what does the organization making that
responds to that look like
I'm kind of curious about what you just
said because something I've been
wondering about through this whole book
is what our board is really necessary
for that meaning making or whether that
can be done in a more distributed way
and I think the Jean tests on this a
little bit in our last call with him
saying that like well this is their job
is to be the board's job specifically
should be able but distinct from the
operation so like they're in this unique
position to really build meaning and
create sense making a facility that
process but I'm wondering if it's
no like actually necessary for that to
happen because it does strike me as like
very top down like imposing a sense
making framework on organization is a
ton of power uh and it does very much
constrain the cognitive abilities of the
larger organization
and
it strikes me just on this simple
reading of it that like maybe something
is missing from that or maybe a
potential other way forward that is less
top-down as possible but I'm probably
misunderstanding Bajan as well so I'm
curious what y'all think
it'll be so fun to explore but let's
just say that the task of strategic
management is organization making
maybe this is a saddle point View
that everybody can get on board with but
then we go great upper Management's role
and function was organization making and
now everyone has access to the tools and
at least view or comment access
to the process of organization making
so
trans morphing
the understanding of what the upper
echelon does
in terms of organization making so just
double checking if you're not involved
in steering the ship you're involved in
organization making and action
orientation
and then perhaps that function
could be
taken on
by another organizational structure
with that as its focus or that could be
an emergent functionality of other
organizational units but it's really
hard to go from Vision coming from the
top to Simply a vision that's coherent
arising from the bottom and from the
outside and so there's an intermediate
view that qualifies the conversation
differently
yeah I think that makes sense so I think
we have observed that since making
happening both in the bottom and the top
and especially in tech companies
um where like you will have a board and
they are making bit like you know
top-down decisions but you will also
have like Consultants almost embedded at
each level of the hierarchy who do that
sense making every level of the
hierarchy uh and bubble that up also to
the top so I think it does exist where
you kind of have it's not purely sense
making happening at the board of their
TMT level
so I just want to point out the first
sentence here and it really resonates
with what you just said entirely like
the way that I've been reading this he
says the critical consideration is how
an organization transmorphs the sensing
and sense making activity at the
individual level into a firm's
institutionalized environmental
enactment as a basis for continuous
strategic renewal like what I took that
like individual level as a very like
bottom-up thing
um because it's like you know each like
little worker Aunt right in the colony
like I I took that as like a very
bottom-up and distributed thing like how
do you take that and turn it into like
some kind of collective sense making but
really that could also be like there's
an individual
um
like level at the top like each board of
directors is selected for their
different expertise right so like you
have a variety I mean ideally you have a
variety of different views and
perspectives at the board level and then
how do those individuals like translate
their sense making into like something
that the institution can then act upon
um so I think that that is a very like
it rings very true that like this
individual
um sensing and sin speaking is happening
at like the top end at the bottom
um I think that that's that that brings
true
though I just want to draw one
distinction based on some experience of
like doing the top down since making so
like I was a strategy consultant for a
while and a lot of times you would do
the top-down uh sense making where you
would like talk to all levels of the
hierarchy and you kind of act as the
board in that situation and kind of
Bubble Up all of this information into
like a top level
um idea about what's happening in the
organization what the narrative is and
what actions they should take and so
it's like very top-down structured but
there's like other models of doing this
where each node and organization is more
or less operating independently and
since making it dependently whereas like
the top-down structure isn't as
important and maybe you're saying the
same thing but it strikes me as like a
little bit different
where sense making isn't happening
through a bubble up process through a
pyramid but rather happening in like a
web okay in a mesh and that strikes me
as like an important difference but
maybe John is saying the same thing I'm
not sure
it's hard to know and it's hard to also
know like how
um you know when you have like even at
like a single layer of the hierarchy
like you have you know 25 people and
like you know 12 of them think one thing
and 13 of them think another thing like
how do you like make sense of that like
where there's this like opposing
Viewpoint how do you collectively like
get buy-in to proceed with like either
strategy a or strategy B like even at a
single level
um and then pass that information up or
down without like well I wanted it to be
this way or I wanted like the people
going
um that like the opposing view like
whatever wins right like in a vote the
13 would win if that's the way that that
it's run or maybe there's weighted
voting or who knows right like however a
firm would structure itself but it's
like really important I think to get
strategy buy-in like from everyone at
least like hear all of the points in
order to to proceed and and
have like the Viewpoint adopted widely
and like get people to get behind it so
it's I don't know it's a hard like weird
thing to think about how that
information is passed up or down in the
hierarchy
all right
Tyler do you have something out
well I was just going to add that
this is a really important point like I
don't think I'm not just trying to be
like pedantic about it like it actually
a lot of organizational strategy debates
hinge on this of whether really you can
do sense making in a like hierarchical
way like truly like a pyramid or like a
more mesh Network so like the mesh
networks are more like teal
organizations or democracies and like
this is a very contentious point and I
was hoping that we could like figure it
out head on or understand the Jean's
like perspective on it and I think he
thinks both are possible because I think
he's hinted at that in the previous live
streams but he hasn't said it like uh
super clearly so far
um but something I've been like very
eagerly waiting for him to like spell
out clearly so maybe he'll get to it in
the next chapters so Tyler like I have a
request like in the next live stream you
have to put in like a slide down
hypocrisy and like explain that to us
like in a very like break it all down
break down all these different like
strategies for us because like you have
that expertise and I'm lost so that
there's there's my special request
okay awesome yeah I mean I've just been
in like lots of debates with even within
especially in Dallas where they try to
do the mesh Network version of things
not the the pyramid and a lot of times
just like a total disaster and it
doesn't work but there's always this
dream especially in Dallas like oh could
this be possible like do you actually
need the hierarchy at all can this work
more like a spider web rather than the
pyramid
um and I've been eating this whole book
I've been like waiting for the answer to
that so I'm excited to ask for joins
yeah and and also just getting these
dimensions
sketched because what if it's like well
yeah we can have a slime mold but then
we may split a lot and not all the
things that split off May survive if
that is tolerable or preferable to you
slime mold it is but if we all wanna
ride or die together then this kind of a
structure is what we want so making sure
that there's like consent and
transparency around what people are
wanting to be in because also in sort of
emergent online 2020s eras teams and
Dows it's like are we hanging out in the
group chat are we building a product
that's going to change the information
environment are we learning about other
projects are we learning about other
early projects invest in like it can
move very rapidly amongst those spaces
and at the risk of trying to capture for
birds and getting none
there's all these other failure modes
but maybe again that's what those people
wanted to do in that blanket at that
time
but when you have shareholders in a
board and there are some
responsibilities that come into play and
these sort of okay to fail or okay to
Sunset experiments in online
organization hopefully can reveal
empirical patterns that we use to carry
forward organizational technique
yeah my reads so far and what John's
doing is that he's saying like yes sure
a slide mold organization is a totally
thing you there's a thing you could
conceive of and like that's a valid way
for thinking about an organization but
he's specifically thinking about like
the legal context that a lot of
organizations live in today and making
uh active inference or free energy
governance work for those organizations
in the world that we live in so I'm not
sure if that resonates with you guys but
oh okay nice nice uh debate tangential I
don't know information dive all right uh
so
um Bijan makes this point and he says
organizations are challenged to better
distinguish how their actions differ
from those of others as they construct
econishas and he um really kind of gives
this like
um like a lot of back a lot of like
background information but I just pulled
these two quotes about like
distinguishing self from other like how
do you distinguish what is me and what
is you and also like about how do you
sense make like help others see what's
in your head
um and in in talking about these things
he gives two examples which I thought
were really cool from biology so I
wanted to read them he quotes Godfrey
Smith 2016 and says whenever a fish
emits a pulse it also sends a copy of
the command around to the sensing system
enabling that system to counteract the
effect of the pulse it has produced The
Fig the fish is tracking and registering
the distinction between self and other
between the effects on its senses of its
own actions and the effects of events
going on around it
um and then he also goes on to say to
use the example of sharks he says sharks
pequots lonza at out this 20 20 paper he
says sharks have organs called lorenzini
blisters which sense electrical Fields
dolphins and tooth whales for example
benefit from echolocation abilities
whose sound pulses can penetrate soft
tissue to provide them with an x-ray
like mental image of the objects of
interest in order to tell the other
Dolphins what they have discovered they
actually create a visual picture of what
they just saw in the minds of other
Dolphins so I didn't like put a full
like explanation of echolocation because
it gets complicated but like here's this
dolphin and it sends out these
echolocation rays and if something is in
its echolocation site because it's not
really sight right but if something it
sees it then the arrays that are
reflected back like give like a are like
molded around so you can imagine like
Whipple ripples through like water right
like so they mold around like a rock or
a stream and so what comes back back is
actually like a physical like Ripple
picture of the rock or whatever it's
seeing and so it can actually then
modify its own like echolocation sounds
to give a picture of the rock to someone
else which I think is so cool right like
like to a dolphin friend no not like
someone else um because I couldn't see a
ripple picture of a rock but maybe it's
dolphin friends could
um anyway I think that that is a neat
idea of how to like really
um you know we always ask people like do
you understand me do you know what I
mean do you really know
um but like it's really hard to know
perceptually what someone else is is
what's behind their markup blanket right
um do you guys have anything to add here
sorry I'm just the one fascinated with
biological sensing and Sun speaking okay
uh Tyler do you want to read this claim
for us
sure so more specifically optimization
is essential across the consist
constituent elements determining the
circular causality of the underlying and
active inference one actions generating
reliable sensory input Precision two the
ability to express beliefs that bad
beliefs consequences sophistication to
enact only a bounded set of external
States three leveraging salience without
missing the very error signaling value
that non-selling stimuli May nonetheless
behold and four foresight to
anticipatory develop and strengthen the
internal States I.E firm resources in
form of capabilities critical to
Resource recombination so sensing sense
making and Duality management
cool I I find it interesting here that
one two and three are within the life
cycle of an organization or an organism
they refer to the reliability of action
the ability to have an appropriately
expanded vocabulary in terms of
sophistication to describe relevant
action and then three essentially
attention which is to make sure that
you're not just falling victim to hyper
skewed or hypernormal stimuli but rather
you're using your attention to enrich
incoming stimuli and also not ignoring
what you're not totally paying attention
to that might be on the margins of
relevance but then four is framed here
as an anticipatory question
in the long run whether the capabilities
are successful to manage resource for
combination that's the question of life
and death
so one two and three are like the
behavioral imperatives and then four is
kind of like the organism looking to the
Horizon maybe it makes it or maybe its
offspring does or maybe none of the
above
thank you
um and then just this final
um quote from from the the paper or from
the book he says Duality is an essential
quantum concept that underpins the
Mastery of managing the distributed and
discontinuous nature of today's market
realities
um and like I'm curious as to like what
Bhajan is referring to as Duality like
in the quantum context I always think
about like wave particle duality but I
think um he has talked here a lot about
superposition and maybe he's referring
to superposition
um maybe he means superposition like you
can exist in two different states you
know until until for a long time like
you can be both black and white one and
zero
um so I'm not I'm not really sure what
he's referring to as Duality but I think
maybe we'll get into it in the next
um
yeah I was curious whether the
connection he's making here is like one
of analogy saying like hey in the same
way you don't know what what's out there
in the quantum world do you only You
observe something and you kind of
collapse all of these waves into
electron is it an analogy in the active
inference free energy governance world
with through you know the inactivist
approach or is he saying that this is
actually like the same thing that is the
same principle underlying and I wasn't
totally sure which way
what he meant there
yes
we should explore there's the wave
particle duality famous there's the
Observer observed Duality or the
experimenter environment duality
there's multiple dualities and then
if we think back to Bayesian physics
what does this help us with
let's go into it more in the next
chapter and then see how it actually
connects back otherwise I I believe it
puts us squarely into the
Quantum business advice
genre but I know there's more to it
man that would be like a very uh
sellable like Quantum business advice
Quantum business strategy manager um
that's my new job I'd be like it's a
heck of a consultant title am I working
am I not working like you could check
you still might not find out
am I here am I there where am I actually
um you can't measure my position and my
momentum at the same time
um that's too funny okay all right
um I think uh we've reached the end of
our set of slides I'm looking forward to
exploring the quantum in more detail
um as I find the quantum Concepts
fascinating I guess bishan also does do
you guys have anything else to add
Before We Say Goodbye
foreign
next week
thanks y'all farewell